Finding Aid for Thomas M. Farrell papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Thomas M. Farrell papers 1947-2011, 1952-2000
Farrell, Thomas M.
1 linear feet
2013128 Aa 2
Papers of Thomas M. Farrell, Michigan political journalist, editor, and State public information officer. Farrell started his career as a correspondent for the United Press International, was Congressman John C. Mackie Administrative Assistant (1965-1966), and at different times served as Public Information Officer for the Michigan State Highway Department (1959-1965) and for the Michigan Supreme Court (1985-1993), Public Information Director for the Michigan Department of Transportation (1966-1968) and Department Commerce (1969-1972), Assistant Superintendent for Public Affairs for the Michigan Department of Education (1972-1985), and as Director of Communications for Michigan Catholic Conference (1968-1969). Collection includes correspondence, research material and articles by and about Farrell, as well as material collected by Farrell on subjects of professional and personal interests, mostly related to Michigan politics, government, and political figures; also photographs and VHS videotapes.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Thomas M. Farrell (donor no. 10877 ) in January 2013
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Thomas M. Farrell is a Detroit, Mich. native. He attended Aquinas College in Grand Rapids and served a two-year term in the U.S. Army. He started his career in the mid-1940s as a sports writer for Grand Rapids Herald and Grand Rapids Press. In 1949 Farrell joined the United Press International (UPI), first in Detroit, then at the Lansing Bureau. In 1954 he became the Grand Rapids Bureau Manager. Farrell was UPI divisional representative for Michigan from 1956 to 1958, then returned to the Grand Rapids Office as Bureau Manager. Farrell covered Michigan Legislature and attended Governor G. Mennen Williams' twice-daily press conferences. The construction and opening of the Mackinac Bridge on November 1, 1957 was one of the major Farrell's stories during his tenure at UPI. He wrote and edited news coverage by staff writers.
In September 1959 Farrell became the Public Information Officer for the Michigan State Highway Department Information Services, under Commissioner John C. Mackie's leadership. At the time Michigan was leading the nation in freeway construction, building the first cross-state interstate freeway (I-94). Among many that Farrell executed, were preparation of daily news releases, road information bulletins, and material for speeches and other presentations by Department personnel, coordination of public events and press conferences, etc. When in 1964 Mackie was elected as a Democrat from Michigan's 7th congressional district to the 89th U.S. Congress, Farrell became Mackie's Administrative Assistant, relocating to Washington, D.C.
After Mackie lost congressional elections to Republican Donald W. Riegle, Jr. in 1966, Farrell returned to Michigan to work as Public Information Director for the State Department of Transportation, then in 1968 he became Director of Communications for the Michigan Catholic Conference. In 1969 Farrell joined the Office of Economic Expansion of the state Department of Commerce. As the Department Public Information Director, he coordinated the public information and promotional activities of all of the Department of Commerce bureaus.
In 1972 Farrell became the Michigan Department of Education Assistant Superintendent for Public Affairs. In this capacity he directed the department's legislative program designed to bring about improvements in the elementary, secondary, and higher education systems in the state; represented the Superintendent of Public Instruction before the legislature, the executive office, the press, the professional and other organizations interested in the improvement of the educational system, and at professional organizations in the development of programs of mutual concern; and selected and utilized the media and techniques necessary for accomplishing the goals and objectives of the public information and legislative programs. Farrell stayed with the Department of Education for 13 years.
In September 1985 Farrell was hired by the Chief Justice and former Michigan Governor G. Mennen Williams as the Michigan Supreme Court Information Officer. Chief Justice G. Mennen Williams announced Farrell's appointment. Farrell was charged with coordination of an expanded communication program that would improve Court's communication with the public, the executive and legislative branches of the State government, and the Michigan legal community. Farrell retired in 1993 at the age of 65.
Since 1977 Farrell has served on the Board of Directors of Blue Lake Fine Arts Camp, a summer camp for the arts located in the Manistee National Forest. Since 1976 Farrell has been involved with the Michigan-Shiga Educational and Cultural Exchange organization, promoting relationship between the state of Michigan and the Prefecture of Shiga, Japan. Farrell is also Past President of the Public Relations Association of Michigan.
The collection is organized into four series: Personal files, Professional files, Subject files, and Audio-Visual material.
Subjects:
Farrell, Thomas M.; Mackie, John C.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Mackinac Bridge (Mich.); Michigan. Department of Education.; Michigan. Department of State Highways.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Reporters and reporting--Law and legislation--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Personal files
  The Personal files series (0.1 linear feet, 1947-2011) job performance evaluations; correspondence, articles, and other material related to Farrell's career and retirement. All correspondence dated after Farrell's retirement in 1993 can be found here.
  - 1947-1985 (Box 1)
  - 1993-2011 (Box 1)
  - Undated (Box 1)
- Professional files
  The Professional files series (0.6 linear feet, 1953-2010) includes material related to the offices where Farrell held positions. For researchers' convenience, material dated before and/or after Farrell's appointment with certain organizations and offices is found here. For example, although Farrell served as the Michigan Catholic Conference Director of Communications only in 1968-1969, this series includes collected Conference material dated between 1955 and 2010. Material related to John C. Mackie can also be found in the Michigan State Highway Department folder, as Farrell and Mackie worked there together before Mackie's term in the U.S. Congress in 1965-1966. Also included in this series subject files related to Farrell's professional activities: writing and correspondence on the subject of Mackinac Bridge and its construction, Governor G. Mennen Williams, some of his early writing, and contents of scrapbook with professional correspondence and newspaper clippings.
  - Camp Atterbury, Indiana 1952 (Box 1)
  - Mackie, John C.
    - 1960-1966 (Box 1)
      (includes photographs)
    - 1992-2008 with gaps (Box 1)
  - Mackinac Bridge
    - 1957-1965 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1982 with gaps (Box 1)
    - 2007 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Catholic Conference 1955-2010 with gaps and undated (Box 1)
  - Michigan Department of Commerce 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Department of Education
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976-1985 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Department of Transportation 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Michigan State Highway Department 1959-1964 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Supreme Court 1985-1994 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 1970-1986 (Box 1)
    (include photograph)
  - United Press Associations 1952-1959 (Box 1)
  - Williams, G. Mennen
    - 1953, 1982-1987 (Box 1)
      includes photograph
    - 1988-2006 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  The Subject files series (0.25 linear feet, 1953-2011) reflects Farrell's intellectual and personal interests. It includes correspondence and newsletters of Michigan-Shiga, Japan Educational and Cultural Exchange, the Blue Lake Fine Arts Camp Board of Trustees correspondence, financial and administrative documentation, reports and articles about the program, letters from Farrell's friend Norman L. Braun, and collected newspaper and journal articles and clippings. Material related to Michigan Historic Preservation includes the 2011 Michigan Historical Commission meeting agenda and meeting. Also included here are preliminary reports of several Michigan Historic District Study Committees charged with identifying, researching, and studying potential historic districts, with comments by the State Historic Preservation Office staff members. Reports include history and summary of historical significance of districts and individual buildings, exterior and interior images, maps and plans. Reports describe the following areas: the University Club in Detroit, First Methodist Episcopal Church in Lansing, Rood Building in Grand Rapids, Hermann's Bakery Building in Royal Oak, Market and Main (Huron) Street in Mackinac Island, West End of Mackinac Island, and Adams Building and Masonic Building in Sault Ste. Marie.
  - Blue Lake Fine Arts Camp 1980-2011 (Box 1)
  - Braun, Norman L 1954, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Brickley, Jim 1982 (Box 1)
  - Historic preservation 2009, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Michigan-Shiga Educational and Cultural Exchange 1976-2011 with gaps and undated (Box 1)
    (includes photograph)
  - Newspaper clippings and articles (Box 1)
- Audio-Visual material
  The Audio-Visual material series (0.05 linear feet, 1962, 1967, 1990 and undated) includes a folder with photographs, mostly undated. Images include autographed portraits of Michigan Governors John B. Swainson and William G. Milliken, Congressman John C. Mackie and other public figures and journalists; autographed portrait of structural engineer and designer of the Mackinac Bridge David B. Steinman, and a view of the Mackinac Bridge. Also included is a Christmas 1962 photo brochure "Who was in charge here?" by the staff of Governor John B. Swainson, with images of Swainson and his wife Alice with national and Michigan political leaders. Two 1990 VHS videotapes have recordings of events related to the Michigan Supreme Court: "Dedication of the Honorable G. Mennen Williams Portrait Special Session of the Michigan Supreme Court to Appear in Vol. 434 of the Michigan Reports" (May 3, 1990, 50 minutes); and "Supreme Court Restoration Meeting: 7/11/90 Lansing." A label on the latter reads "Tape 2 of 2."
  - Photographs 1960s, undated (Box 1)
  - Videotapes
    - Dedication of the Honorable G. Mennen Williams portrait special session of the Michigan Supreme Court..., 1990 (Box 1)
    - Supreme Court restoration meeting 1990 (Box 1)